Finding aid for Peter Sparling papers, 1961-2013 0312 Aa2
Bentley Historical Library
- Performance, Audition, and Rehearsal Videos
  The Performance, Audition, and Rehearsal Videos series, (1 linear foot, 1 outsized box, and 96 GB 1972-2012), documents a variety of Sparling's performances, screendances, auditions, and rehearsals from 1972 to 2013. The series is arranged alphabetically by the title of the work and includes six reels of film (ca. 1947-1972), 45 VHS videocassettes (1977-1994), 33 digital videocassettes (1981-2001; transferred from Hi-8, U-matic, S-VHS, and VHS formats), two DVDs (2004-2005), and 23 digital video files (featuring works from 1994 to 2013).
  Taken as a whole, the series illustrates the range and depth of Sparling's work as a dancer, choreographer, director, and innovator in recording techniques. Highlights include five reels of 8 mm home film footage from Sparling's childhood (used in his work, "In Stride"), a film reel of a 1972 performance by Sparling and Janet Eilber of a Doris Humphrey work, nine VHS cassettes of dances from 1977-1981 recovered by the New York Public Library's Dance Division from badly-deteriorated one half inch open reel tapes, and 37 S-VHS videocassettes documenting the Martha Graham Dance Company's four days in residence at the University of Michigan as part of the 1994 Martha Graham Centenary Festival (presented by Sparling, the University of Michigan Dance Department and the University Musical Society). The 1999 "1-Inflow/Outflow" project, an experiment in technology-enabled distance cooperation among several disciplines, includes a performance of Sparling's piece "The Ariel Web." Other recordings emphasize Sparling's accomplishments as a dancer ("Swing Serenade" "Bride of Grand Prairie" and "What She Forgot He Remembered") educator ("Heart's Crossing"), and choreographer ("Dance for 'The Wave Field'" and "Orfeo ed Euridice"). In the 2000s and 2010s, Sparling's dancepoems ("The Snowy Owl"), screendances ("Paris Accelerations" and "Babel") and collaborations ("Photoformance: Long Lie Down") are a testament to his continuing productivity and relevance. Performances in the series also feature members of the Peter Sparling Dance Company, Ann Arbor Dance Works, Peter Sparling Presents Solo Flight, and University of Michigan Dance Company.
  - The Albion Dance Project: Reflets dans l'eau, October 17, 1992; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar032 (Box 6)
  - Allegorica: A Videodance Vaudeville in Nine Acts, 2007
    - Installation Documentation, .MPEG file
      Reading Room Access Only
    - Performance, .MPEG file
  - Babel (Screendance), 2005; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Beautiful Captives, 2012; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - black body (Screendance), 2010; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - The Boy Who played with Dolls, circa 1991; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar018 (Box 6)
  - Bright Bowed River, circa 1985; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar013 (Box 6)
  - Chaconne, circa 1986; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar012 (Box 6)
  - Climbing Sainte-Victoire (Screendance), 2008; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Dance for The Wave Field, October 6, 1995; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar026 (Box 6)
  - Dance Uptown Earl Hall, city unknown, December 1, 1977; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Dances We Dance, undated; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar023 (Box 6)
  - Danced Improvisations to Bach and Schubert University of Michigan Duderstadt Center, March 2, 2005; DVD (Box 6)
  - "Day on Earth,", May 1972 (Box 4)
    Performance of Doris Humphrey's 1947 directed by Jose Limon, music by Aaron Copland ("Piano Sonata"), performed by Janet Eilber, Peter Sparling, Ann deGange and Elizabeth Haight.
  - De Profundis, circa 1989; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar004 (Box 6)
  - The Death of Saint Narcissus, 2012; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - DEVANT/DERRIERE (Screendance), 2009; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Divining Rod, circa 1981; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar020 (Box 6)
  - Door to the River (featuring the University Dance Co.), 2010; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - A Fearful Symmetry, circa 1984; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar030 (Box 6)
  - From Rust and Ruin, (Screendance), 2004; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Forest Through the Trees, (University Dance Co.), 2011; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Four Ballads, not dated, DVC-Pro digital cassette spar031 (Box 6)
  - He was Locked in a Race Against Time, 2008; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Heart's Crossing, circa 1988; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar017 and spar033 (Box 6)
  - In Memorium: Shirley Verrett (Screendance) 2010, .MOV and .MP4 files
  - "In Stride,"undated, 5 reels of 8 mm film (Box 4)
  - Internet2 Demo Project 1-Inflow/Outflow (Office of the Vice President for Research Discretionary Fund Application: The Ariel Web), October 12, 1999; VHS videocassette (Box 3)
  - Iris and Fearful Symmetry, October 16, 1981; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Iris and Viola Songs, circa 1981; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar035 (Box 6)
  - Last Man at Willow Run (Screendance), 2013; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Le Fils des Etoiles (featuring Matthew Farmer), 2008; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - L'Histoire du Soldat, circa 1987; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar029 (Box 6)
  - Martha Graham Centenary Festival Project, October 1994; 37 S-VHS videocassettes (Box 3)
    Tapes are not playable at the Bentley Library, see Reference Archivist; index in front of box.
  - New Bach, circa 1996; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar008 (Box 6)
  - Nocturne, circa 1986; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar024 (Box 6)
  - Nocturnes for Euridice, circa 1984; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar021 (Box 6)
  - Orfeo ed Euridice, June 11, 2001; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar001 (Box 6)
  - Orfeo ed Euridice (Michigan Theatre performance) June 11, 2001., VHS videocassette (Box 3)
  - Once in a Blue Moon, Riverside Dance Festival, New York, May 16, 1978; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Orion The Juilliard Theater, New York, May 13, 1980; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Paris Accelerations (Screendance), 2010; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Paris Triptyques (Screendance), 2010; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Patient Spider (Screendance), 2011; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Petruschka, circa 1989; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar001 (Box 6)
  - Photoformance: Long Lie Down, 2011; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Reel, circa 1983; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar022 (Box 6)
  - Repertory Works, DVC-Pro digital cassette spar034 (Box 6)
  - Rondo, circa 1987; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar014 (Box 6)
  - Round Dance, circa 1983; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar037 (Box 6)
  - Rounding the Square, circa 1989; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar006 (Box 6)
  - Seven Enigmas, 1997; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - The Snowy Owl (Dancepoem), 2012; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Solos and Transfigurations, Choreography and Improvisation, University of Michigan Dance Gallery, November-February 2004; DVD (Box 6)
    - Winter Study (Box 6)
    - Song Without Words (Box 6)
    - Thoreau/Ives (Box 6)
    - From Rust and Ruin (A Solo for Peninsula) (Box 6)
    - Riff and Transfiguration (Box 6)
    - Let me Lament (Box 6)
  - Suite to Sleep, Riverside Dance Festival, New York, May 11, 13, 14, 1978; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Swing Serenade, circa 1982; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar036 (Box 6)
  - A Thief's Progress, Riverside Dance Festival, New York, May 11, 13, 14, 1978; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Three Etudes, circa 1990; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar005 (Box 6)
  - Travelogue, circa 1994; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar010 (Box 6)
  - Travelogue, 1994; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Untitled, undated., VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - Unfinished/Tanzmuzik, circa 1997; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar007 (Box 6)
  - UNTRANSLATABLE!, 2010; .MOV and .MP4 files
  - Viola Sonatas, undated; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar028 (Box 6)
  - Warm-up Routine, undated; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar016 (Box 6)
  - What She Forgot He Remembered, December 1979; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - What She Forgot He Remembered The Juilliard Theater, New York, January 1980; VHS videocassette (Box 6)
  - What She Forgot He Remembered, undated; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar026 (Box 6)
  - Wings, circa 1989; DVC-Pro digital cassette spar003 (Box 6)
  - Wintertanze I, DVC-Pro digital cassette spar025 (Box 6)
- Posters, 1974-1994
  The final series is POSTERS, (20 linear feet, 1974-1994). Included are a number of posters from various performances by Sparling or of one of his works. They are dated from 1974 to 1994. Also included in this series are thirteen oversized drawings. The drawings are mainly artist's sketches in pastel, ink, and watercolors that were later used for program covers.
  - Posters, 1974-1994; undated (Box 5)
  - Drawings (13), undated (Box 5)